<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="article.css"?>
<document xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<banner>Recursions and Ruminations</banner>
  <page>
    <header>
      <title>Will Web Services Break the Semantic Web?</title>
      <author>Kurt Cagle</author>
      <primaryLink>http://www.kurtcagle.net/articles/brokenSemantics.xml
                                                                 </primaryLink>
    </header>
    <body>
      <para>The Semantic Web has been a central concept in web development since
        Tim Berners Lee's seminal paper on the subject, <jump 
        xlink:href="http://www.w3.org/DesignIssues/Semantic.html"
        xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace">A roadmap to the Semantic
        Web</jump> in 1998 (with a more popular description of the Semantic Web
        in <jump xlink:href="http://www.scientificamerican.com/2001/0501issue/
       0501berners-lee.html" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="replace">Scientific
        American</jump> in 1999.In it he posited that while the World Wide Web 
        has become largely readible to people, no consistent mechanism existed 
        for being able to create associations between different types of data 
        that could be used to make inferences. The ability to identify a block 
        of data as being a "thing" of a certain type is crucial to being able to 
        manipulate that thing. Thus, ultimately, the purpose of the semantic web 
        (as he saw it) was to provide an architecture that would not only make 
        it possible to objectify the web but to do so in a way that required 
        relatively little human intervention.
      </para>
      <para>The original vision that Berners-Lee had of this Semantic web 
        depended upon a standard that is still relatively obscure today, though 
        it is growing in popularity. The Resource Description Framework 
        language, or RDF, can seem fairly abstruse -- it's primary purpose is to
        provide a framework for describing the associations between one or more 
        resources on the web. A simple relationship, <term>equivalence</term> 
        for instance, could be used to indicate that an XML element in one 
        schema (such as a <element>lastname</element>) was equivalent to a 
        <element>familyName</element> element in a different schema. By having 
        this relationship clarified, it means that if a program could read 
        <element>lastname</element> elements, they could work with 
        <element>familyName</element> elements in the same way, even if the rest 
        of the schema was very different.
      </para>
      <para>One consequence of such a relationship mechanism is that the 
        disparate data stores can be used to aggregate and filter data in a much
        more transparent fashion. Through such a system, for instance, you can 
        create an aggregate bibliography of everything a person may have written
        on the web, for instance, making it possible to build a comprehensive 
        portfolio of their works in ways that would be almost impossible to do
        on the web. It also makes patterns far more obvious, as an RDF-centric 
        Internet tends to emphasize the relationships between entities, rather 
        than the specific characteristics of the entities themselves.
      </para>
<!-- additional content -->
    </body>
  </page>
</document>



